<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="servicehandler">
  <title>Service Handler bindings</title>
  <para><emphasis>Service Handler Bindings</emphasis> are used to allow the declaration of
    interfaces and abstract classes as implemented beans. Any call to an abstract method on the
    interface or abstract class will be forwarded to the invocation layer for processing. This
    specification defines a typesafe mechanism for associating service handlers to abstract classes
    and interfaces using <emphasis>service handler bindings</emphasis>.</para>
  <para>
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A <emphasis>Service Handler</emphasis> is different from a
            <emphasis>Decorator</emphasis> so that the interface is unknown at runtime. </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>A <emphasis>Service Handler</emphasis> is different from an
            <emphasis>Interceptor</emphasis> so that the implementation of the method is provided
          instead of cross-cutting concerns.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <section id="servicehandlerbindings">
    <title>Service Handler binding types</title>
    <para>A <emphasis>service handler binding type</emphasis> is a Java annotation defined as
        <literal>@Target({TYPE, METHOD})</literal> or <literal>@Target(TYPE)</literal> and
        <literal>@Retention(RUNTIME)</literal>.</para>
    <para>An service handler binding type may be declared by specifying the
        <literal>@javax.servicehandler.ServiceHandlerBinding</literal> meta-annotation.</para>
    <programlisting>@Inherited
@ServiceHandlerBinding
@Target({TYPE, METHOD})
@Retention(RUNTIME)
public @interface QueryService {}</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section id="declaringinterceptor">
    <title>Declaring the service handler binding of a service handler</title>
    <para>The service handler binding of a service handler is specified by annotating the service
      handler class with the binding type and the
        <literal>@javax.servicehandler.ServiceHandler</literal> annotation.</para>
    <para>
      <programlisting>@Retention(RUNTIME)
@Target({METHOD})
@interface Query {   
     String value();   
}</programlisting>
    </para>
    <programlisting>@QueryService @ServiceHandler
public class QueryServiceHandler {

   @Inject    
   javax.persistence.EntityManager em;     

   @AroundInvoke 
   public Object handleQueryInvocation(InvocationContext ctx) throws Exception {
      return em.createQuery(ctx.getMethod().getAnnotation(Query.class).value()).getResultList();
   }

}</programlisting>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Binding a service handler to a bean</title>
    <para>A service handler binding may be declared by annotating a interface or an abstract class,
      with the service handler binding type.</para>
    <para>In the following example, the <literal>QueryServiceHandler</literal> will be applied at
      the class level, and therefore applies to all business methods of the class:</para>
    <programlisting>@QueryService
public interface ProductDAO{

     @Query("select obj from Product obj where obj.productName like ?")
     List&lt;Product> getAllProducts();

}</programlisting>
    <para>An abstract class or interface may define multiple service handlers.</para>
    <para>If a service handler binding annotation is specified on an abstract method, the called
      service handler applied will be .</para>
  </section>
</chapter>
